Professor
Enri College Michael Bert
Mike Bert. Michael welcome.
Yeah. Hola.
Hello to everyone.
Yes.
Mig or Miguel as I call him. Miguel.
Miguel
I see. Well, Mike, and now we're gonna
go into the book, but first tell us um
briefly um where you're from, what you
do,
if you might.
Yeah. Well, I'm Mike. I live in
Melbourne, Australia. I teach at Ridley
College. I teach New Testament, a bit of
theology. I do a bit of writing, do a
podcast with Tom Wright. That's pretty
much my claim to fame.
Four kids. I've never been to Argentina,
but I do like the musical Avita.
Oh, you like Avita? [laughter]
Yeah.
You know, if by saying that you kind of
divided Argentina in two. [laughter]
Yes.
Yeah. I Hey, I I'm saying I like the
musical. I'm not saying I like Peronism.
I just I just like the musical.
[laughter]
It's just great music.
I don't know.
If you ever come, if you ever go to
Argentina, maybe has to um to um to hire
some bodyguards for you now. [laughter]
[gasps] That's how bad it is. Yeah.
Do you want to say anything?
Uh yes, we have a very difficult
economical situation.
I thought the man with the chainsaw
fixed that.
Not too much.
Not so much. Don't you know uh Mike,
they're eating donkey?
Yes.
Yes. [laughter] Remember it was in the
news too. Yeah. They're eating donkey.
So it's because um because beef is so so
expensive.
So um and remember Argentina is one of
the two biggest um cattleers. Yes.
Yeah.
So they don't have they cannot pay. So
that's that's I mean that's how
Argentinians see their economy. If they
don't have beef, everything's bad.
[laughter]
Anyway, so so we're happy to have you,
Mike, and uh we're going to um make some
questions uh regarding this book. Um so,
um your book presents seven things,
Michael, with you wish every Christian
knew about the Bible.
If tomorrow every Christian in the world
could fully understand just one of those
seven things, which one would you choose
and why?
Uh very good question.
I I think probably the the number one
thing they need to understand
is how the Bible is from God, but it
also involves human processes.
So you've got, you know, authors and you
when authors when I Isaiah writes Isaiah
or Luke writes Luke, they don't go into
a trance and kind of wake up with the
Bible, you know, or a book written in
front of them. a lot of their own
experience, their own understanding of
history,
their own calling, the needs of the
community they're writing to, a lot of
historically contingent factors shape
the way they write. And I I think you've
got to understand that the contingency,
the context in which ancient authors are
being used by God to to bring his word
to us. Uh because the danger is if if
you think of the Bible just as a human
book like one of many religions. I think
that that gets a very low view of
scripture. But then some people think of
the Bible as a magic book as it just
fell out of heaven, you know, bound in
leather, the words of Jesus in red
complete with footnotes and ribbon and
charts and maps. It'd be nice, but
that's that's that's not the way it was
given to us. So I think we have to
understand something a more complex view
of how scripture came to us. And if I
had to add a second one that would be
how does scripture in its totality point
to Christ? Because the first person to
to interpret scripture in light of Jesus
was Jesus himself. So you got the
resurrection narrative in Luke 24 where
you know Jesus meets the two travelers
on the road to Emmas and he says you
know beginning with Moses and all of the
prophets he explained to the things in
scripture concerning himself. Now on the
one hand that can lead people to what
you might call Jesusifying. I don't know
how to put that into Spanish but to make
everything about Jesus in a real cheesy
way or almost allegorical.
That's an extreme. But there is a sense
in which the totality of scripture does
provide testimony to Christ. And I think
that's something, you know, very
important to to capture. That that would
be the the two top things I would take
away and I I think will be enduring for
for Christians throughout the ages to
remember that irrespective of where they
are from Argentina to Zimbabwe.
Yeah. um being juific.
You just coined a new word. I mean
[laughter]
so yeah. Well, see this is the first in
this in this video in this channel. So
that you you just coined a new word.
All right, you have a next question.
Yes.
As people we discover how the Bible was
actually formed, it authors, literary
genres, historical context and
transmission. Some find that their faith
becomes stronger while others feel
shaken. What do you think makes the
difference between those two reactions?
Yeah.
Yeah. I remember reading uh about
Francis Schaefer's son who somewhat left
the faith through a very secuitous and
and complex route. And he he kind of
like became spiritual but not religious.
And one of the things he said, I want
people to believe in God but without the
Bible. And for me, I just found that
very strange since I know maybe because
I'm a I'm a biblical scholar, but I
think one of the best things about
Christianity is the Bible. I mean, I
really I really I mean, I enjoy all of
it. Like the, you know, creation story
in Genesis, historical narrative, it's
like the history books, it's like Game
of Thrones, but it's got God in it. uh
Psalms, Proverbs, Apocalypse, stories of
Jesus, story of the early church,
epistles. I just the book of Revelation.
I just find everything so literary rich
and interesting. So, but so I I I I just
I I don't understand how some people
think the Bible is an obstacle to their
faith. But then it makes me think, well,
how could the Bible be an obstacle to
their faith? And do they struggle with
the wroth of God? you know, some of the
things that get commanded in scripture,
like when there's warfare between
different tribes in Canaan. So, I try to
put myself in their position to think
sympathetically. And I think there's
there are there is a lot of things that
you read in scripture that are that are
hard, that are jarring, that stop and
make you think. And you you do have to
wrestle with them. Uh [snorts] but but I
think it's because people always come to
scripture with their own biography,
their own their own autobiography, their
own story, their own experiences, maybe
bad things that have been said to them
or happened to them in the church or in
different faith communities. And there
can be things in scripture that are very
jarring. But if you if you remember the
the goodness of God and that you know
God is good to us in Christ Jesus then
whatever difficulties we have in
scripture and I wouldn't deny them for a
moment. whatever difficulties they are,
I think there's always a way to to get
maybe not around them, but to get
through them or learn to persevere or
just put things you don't understand to
the side in the hope that one day you
will have the right perspective on them.
So, I've never understood the uh you
know, I like God, but I'm not I don't
like the Bible. But, you know, there are
some people for whom that is that is a
big problem. Uh I I just for those
people I just hope they they have newer
or different experiences that will lead
them to a a better experience of the God
of the Bible who is a God of grace, a
God of love and a God of mercy.
Uh because in Latin America we have a
lot of u acquaintances DO has and I that
they um they either starts uh reading a
book even by um let's say I'm looking at
some [snorts] people here even by some
um scholars Catholic scholars and they
start doubting the Bible and these are
the scholars who teach at um
at Pontipical uh schools um divinity
schools and but they say oh they because
they are post-graduate books for
post-graduate people and they have never
done any Bible study they they um absorb
all these theories and they said oh this
is what Christianity really is and and I
always say in my videos this is a uh
this is a um a progression first you
start to you have to study um
introductions to New Testament and Old
Testament so you can absorb all this
knowledge but you just jump from one
thing
to another it's like giving a newborn a
piece piece of beef. [laughter] Talking
about beef before
which they don't have in Argentina
anymore because they keep exporting it
telling donkey donkey.
Yeah. No, I I got a donkey.
Um yeah, I got an email the other day
from a guy who says he'd been listening
to a lot of critical scholars and he
felt like his faith was faltering and he
was [clears throat] struggling. And I
said, 'Well, stop listening to these
critical scholars if they're if they're
annoying you or upsetting you so much.
You you've got to remember that most
critical scholars,
their their their theories or their
ideas, some may be mainstream,
but some of them are also contestable
and waiting to be overturned. Like I
remember when everybody said that the
the pentitute, you know, the the first
five books of the Old Testament that was
a result of Jedp theory. So five
distinct sources
and that was the assured results. Nobody
doubted that. No one believes that
anymore. No one believes that there are
just these Jedp authors who wrote the
whole penitent. Um there may be a
priestly redaction of the Torah after
the exile. there's a strong, you know,
maybe Deuteronomic core, but no one can
claim to know with certainty how the the
pentache was put together. You've got a
body of traditions associated with Moses
before the exile, then after the exile,
they seem to be, you know, edited and
put together in a certain way.
But even that's kind of speculative. So
you know once upon a time critical
scholars said we we know from the
assured results of scientific study of
the Bible that the Old Testament the
penetr was compiled by these sources Jed
D and P. We don't believe that anymore.
And you know once upon a time they said
you know the gospel of John it's
historically unreliable. I mean John
[clears throat] invents a place called
the pool of Sylum. I mean there was no
such thing as the pool of Silomme. Lo
and behold,
uh, the when the archaeologists do some
digging around Jerusalem, guess what
they find? They find the pool of Sylum.
And I could go on. I mean, once upon a
time, they said, you know, um,
the the evangelists are wrong because
they call
they call Pilot a prefect rather than a
procurator. They made a big mistake with
him on on on they got they get his title
wrong but then they dig up an
inscription at Caesar Maritima where
he's called a prefect and the title
procurator was not used until much later
in the post70 period. So every now and
again the assured results of critical
study of the Bible uh seems to get
disproved by new evidence or there's new
critical theories that emerge. So you
you if you can't if you can't tie your
faith I don't think you can tie your
faith to apologetics because some
apologetics can be a bit sloppy or there
are some answers apologetics
is better than others in terms of
quality control.
You can't base your faith on apologetics
but you can't base your unfaith on
critical theories because these critical
theories rise and fall.
So that's that's what I tell people you
know what is what is the assured results
one day will be disproved in 10 years
time. That's a great answer and I always
tell him, you know,
one second a boy calling
boy.
I just want wanted to say that the the
man who introduced um the Jedp theory
bailous and he was a Christian.
Yeah,
he was a Christian and he when he saw
that the his students were rejecting
Christianity, he quit. he quit uh
because he had a Christian commitment.
Um so this is where [laughter]
people from B any words?
Yeah,
I was thinking about
no politanism. That is something that
William Le Gray recently
said.
What did he say?
He invented the term neoapolitanism.
Neoism. Yeah.
Yeah. He's I like I like Bill Craig, but
that theory he's got is a little bit
strange.
Yes. [laughter]
I I just I just like I was actually I
mean last night I've been reading about
Apollina
um about his view and he was trying to
um continue the tradition of Athanasius.
So he thought he was following
Athanasius in his view of the
incarnation. But I think he just took a
good thing too far and it was so much so
that the divinity and the humanity comes
from heaven since a pollinarius thought
you know when Paul says you know uh the
second Adam is the man from heaven he
thought even Jesus's humanity came from
heaven and William Lra is trying to do
something similar not exactly the same
but yeah I think there's better ways is
there's much better ways of doing it.
Mhm. Yes. All right. Well, continue. Um
the question number three, the cross
crossing the cultural gap in an ordinary
Christian if an ordinary Christian
wanted to take just one step toward
understanding the Bible better. What
What would you recommend? What's the
most helpful starting point? Historical
context, biblical theology, archaeology,
something else or a combination of
those? I mean, I told you and when when
we did this question, I said, "No, no,
he's going to recommend his biblical
theology."
Well, I would say I I would say all of
it. You need to understand biblical
theology in light of the overall
storyline. So when you when you
understand a verse in Isaiah, you have
to understand it in the context of
Isaiah, but you also have to understand
it in the context of ancient Israel in
the 8th century, but also where it fits
in the storyline in the Bible as a
whole, how it relates to the new
covenant and Jesus. Uh, the other thing
you have to think about is your own
cultural biases. Um, I actually remember
the first time I met a woman from
Argentina and it it it really shocked me
because they literally picked her up
from the airport and brought her to
church and she had an Australian friend
with her and they said like, you know,
this is our friend, you know, Wanita.
And a nice to meet you. And I put my
hand out to meet her and the next thing
I know this woman lunges at me and
kisses me on both cheeks. And I'm kind
of like just stunned like [laughter]
like what has happened? Have I broken
some laws? I don't know. And my friend
quickly had to say no no you cannot do
that here. You cannot just just shake
hands.
But you know we all bring some sort of
you know cultural um baggage with us
which can be a help or a hindrance in
how we understand the Bible. So you know
that's that's very important. How do
your own presuppositions
uh affect the way you read the Bible?
And you know, I know this when I when I
discuss uh things with my American
friends like um guns and healthcare. I
mean, they believe things there that no
other Christian in the world believes.
No, I mean, no Christians don't believe
in the right to bear arms and form
militias. We all prefer a world where
there are no guns. So I find some of not
all but some of my American Christian
friends just very peculiar because we
are all products of our own environment.
Now I'm sure there's an Australian
equivalent of that as well, a you know
Guatemalan, Argentinian views of that.
So you've all got always got to remember
nobody has a God's eye view of
scripture. We all view it through our
own experience, our own church
denomination,
our own history, our own culture. And
sometimes it can help us see things, you
know, in the Bible, you know, more
clearly because we can relate to the
original author and recipients. But
sometimes we're projecting our own
culture into the Bible to get it
validated. Okay? So I say be less
critical of the Bible and more critical
of your own way of reading the Bible.
And that's why I think it's important
that you read scripture with other
people and from other people who read
the Bible from outside your own culture.
Okay? Because that can be incredibly
illuminating because the things that you
may notice or the things that stand out
to you may not be the things that stand
out to others. I mean a good example of
that there's a you know a verse in the
the pastoral epistles which it says
women should dress in modesty which you
know uh I've got some one friend thought
oh well women shouldn't you know show
too much flesh so no plunging necklines
keep it you know modest and discreet
where others said no the issue is not
the amount of clothing you're wearing
it's about how much bling you're showing
how much jewelry do you have like
ostentatious you know
necklaces and rings and earrings and
tiaras and that kind of stuff. It's it's
more about ostentatious well. So what
does it mean to dress moderately
um or in moderation? I mean your own
presuppositions can affect the way you
think about that. So you've got to you
know view your own reading experience
critically and the best way to do that
is to read the Bible with people who are
very different to you.
Uh when you mentioned about the kids uh
my son knows you. He's been watching
your videos. He's 21.
And he would say and he would say,
"That's your Austin Powers looks
[laughter]
that that bring people to you."
Yeah. I've been I've been called the
Austin Powers of Biblical Studies many
times.
Actually, I just I just read today
they're going to make another Austin
Powers movie.
Oh, maybe maybe they'll they invite you
to to do [laughter] a double or
something. But what I mean
maybe I can be Austin P um twin brother.
Twin brother. Yes. the long last
brother. So, um I always talk about this
with my Mexican friends because in the
Bible it says in Romans to greet each
other with a holy kiss, but in in
Mexico, in El Salvador, where I'm from,
that would be like a big no. No, men
don't kiss at all. Well, in Argentina,
they do.
Yeah, I I've learned the hard way. I
learned the hard way.
Yes. Well, um next question, Bill, your
number four.
And first I was going to ask about uh
some books you could recommend to people
about the last question.
Uh books to help them.
Yes.
Oh, that's a very good question. I'll be
I'll be honest. My knowledge of books
published in Spanish is pretty limited.
No, no, that's okay. In English,
I know I know a couple of I know a
couple of my books have been done in
Spanish. um uh apart from that but in
terms of ones that are in English
uh you know I I have read a a couple I
mean there's a couple of books where
they give you perspectives on the Bible
from people around the world and
actually let me give you let me give you
a good example of this I listened to a
very good podcast with a lady called
Elizabeth Maburo who's a East African
scholar she's from Kenya and she pointed
something out that really made me think.
She says, "When when Arab people write a
commentary on the New Testament, they
call it the Arab commentary of the New
Testament. When Africans write a
commentary on the New Testament, they
call it the Arab, sorry, the African
commentary on the New Testament. When
Asians write a commentary on the New
Testament, it's called an Asian
commentary on the New Testament. When
white people write a commentary on the
New Testament, it's called a commentary
on the New Testament, they don't add the
adjective, you know, white people. So
there's there's an Arab commentary, an
African commentary, an Asian commentary,
but what I do is a Anglo. I'm just doing
a commentary as if as if what I do is
just normal,
you know, neutral, what everyone should
be doing. And then there's all these
sort of weird things on the edges.
There's Arabs, Africans, and they've got
some weird things of whether they
interpret the New Testament, but it
never occurs to anyone, maybe I'm the
weird one. Maybe I've got my own um you
know, my own prejudices, my own bias, my
own unique perspective because of my
cultural location. So, uh yeah, I
thought I thought Elizabeth did a very
that was a very good podcast that she
did. It really it really made me think
books like the New Testament in Color,
which is a commentary on the New
Testament from around the world. Uh
there's a few good um Gosh,
I don't know if you noticed. I don't
know if you noticed. I don't know if you
noticed.
Actually, I think I have it on my shelf.
I mean,
yes,
you have it in Spanish already.
Oh, I know. Sorry. I've got the uh an
African.
Okay. Okay. Yes.
Introduction to the New Testament.
There's also another one. Um this I
thought was this was pretty good. Um,
the New Testament in Color I thought was
a good book as well. Um, so there's a
few a few things that my advice is just
read read stuff on the Bible written by
people who don't look like you. That's I
think one of the best things you can do.
And that's why, you know, um,
[clears throat] you know, so don't just
read all your books by Entie Wright, all
your books by
that's what we're putting on the on the
screen right now.
Yeah. Well, look, I want you to read
some antibride, but don't read only
Entride.
Yes, antide
other things as well.
This is coming.
I much I much prefer that that cover
than the Brazilian cover.
Oh, wow. Okay. Yes.
If you can find the Brazilian cover,
you'll um you can you can you can see
Anti Wright's name is like this and my
name is like this. It's like
The [laughter] Yeah, I can imagine the
editorial meeting was like anti- rise
macho macho excellente you know Michael
Bird like that
insignificant
insignificant well um so this is coming
in January 12 2027
so um so we are we everybody's just like
okay
mucho bueno
mucho mucho so this is the type of
things that that I think it will be good
for um
um for people to read but like you said
was also good. Let me tell you this from
a Latin American perspective and knows
this too. If a Latin American writes
something from a Latin American
perspective, Americans people from the
United States usually say it's liberal
because it's looking at from
people at least from El Salvador how
much money they make as a theologian.
for per hour. And my friend who teaches
in supposed to be the best evangelical
theological university in Los Salvador,
he makes $8.50 an hour.
Oh wow. So I I want to make a video
asking then how do you expect that
Latinos can make good theology if they
can barely make a living in El Salvador
at least and and some other the most
that I heard that they can get paid uh
talking about Mexico now which is the
the biggest country in Latin America for
evangelicals
um he makes $16 an hour. So, so I don't
know if here uh I don't think that's
even the minimum wage uh here in
Australia. Mike,
yeah. No, I don't think it is. I don't
think it is. Yeah. I mean, I've been in
other countries uh in India
visiting a theological college where the
lecturers were paid I think even less
than that. Uh so it is a concern. Uh
well, it depends on different parts of
the world. But you know it's important
that we resource theological education
in our own countries
you know wherever they are. So you know
we can have good professors um people
training ministers you know creating the
next generation of Christian thought
leaders and you know to do that you've
got to make the the correct investment
in them.
Yeah. Okay. Next question then better if
you don't have anything.
Number four. The question number four is
about many Christians eventually
encounter apparent contradictions,
historical questions or difficult
passages in scripture. When that
happens, what is the wrong way to
respond and what will be a healthy
faithful way to approach those
challenges?
Yeah, this is a good question. I I
recently watched a video uh an interview
on on YouTube with a guy called uh
Jonathan Boo or B who interviewed
Princeton theologian Dale Allison. And
Dale Allison's a very very good scholar.
Yes.
Very good guy on the gospels. Uh a
little bit kind of a spiritual seeker as
well. Uh a little can be a little
esoteric. But he says that the when the
church the church had a choice to either
follow the church father origin or to
follow the church father Augustine and
how they understand scripture. Augustine
who on the one hand wanted the script
scriptures to be literally true but
allegorically meaningful
whereas origin was a bit different. He
wanted he didn't really care if
scripture was historically true because
he thought there are like he thought
there's some historical problems in
scripture like did Jesus cleanse the
temple at the beginning of his ministry
like in John or at the end in the other
gospels and he thought well you can't
really reconcile them maybe John's just
reorganized things or put in a different
order we don't know but Augustine wanted
to kind of reconcile and harmonize
everything origin recognized there's
some things you just can't harmonize you
just have to live with the tension
And you know, I I'm starting to think
that maybe Origin had a better approach
where you just accept that everything is
not neat and tidy. You just live you
just live in the tension. Now again, I
think there are some harmonizations that
do approach that do work. Um Michael
Lone has got a very good little book
talking about how you know how you can
understand some of the alleged
contradictions in the gospels. I think
that is a very good work and that's
about understanding the ancient genre of
history you know uh in you know the the
way it can be done the way it can be
written in antiquity in the ancient
world and so I'm starting to think you
may maybe even for those who lean more
towards Augustine need a little bit of
origin you've just got to learn that
ultimately
our faith is in God
and we we listen adhere and obey the
Bible, but our ultimate faith is in God.
And if there are some things in
scripture that trouble us, I think you
just you just put them to a side and one
day they'll kind of be resolved, you
know, or figured out. And the other
thing you have to learn to live with is
you have to learn to live with ambiguity
that things don't always match up neatly
and tidily. And for people who are very
systematic, you like you like a box for
everything. and everything lines up.
That can be very that can be very
dissatisfying and it can be very
frustrating. Um some people understand
that you have to learn with messiness.
Okay. And yet there are things like you
know in scripture we we know God is both
love but God has a sense of justice that
can burn with wroth against evil. So how
do you reconcile God's love with God's
wroth? People have been wrestling that
with a with a long time. There are some
historical issues like when did Jesus
have the last supper? Was it on the
night before Passover or in John's
account was it a few days like you know
was it just a few days before the proper
Passover you know so you know did John
change it to make a theological point or
did Jesus have a quasi Passover meal
because he knew he would not live long
enough to have the actual Passover or as
I think I mean you know there's a
million people in Jerusalem I don't
think they could all get their lamb
stored on the same day So, I wonder if
everybody had to stagger their Passovers
across the week. I mean, I just don't
know. And I don't I don't think anyone
knows. We know that there is a slight
difference in the chronology between the
synoptics and John's gospel that I've
got a few theories and a few ideas. Um,
but if I if someone convinced me that
John has deliberately altered it, I'm
not going to abandon my faith. I mean,
it's a silly thing to abandon your faith
over because the evangelist has made one
slight change in in one of the details.
So, you know, you you've got to learn to
live with messiness, untidiness,
incompleteness.
And things in scripture may not be true
in the way that we were assuming they
must be true. Okay? At the end of the
day, I believe scripture is true and
trustworthy because God is true and
trustworthy. Okay? And scripture will
never lead us astray, but it will always
tell us what we need to know about God,
about history, uh about what happened.
And in the general outlines, I I believe
it is I believe that is the case. So I I
think you you've got to learn to live
with some degree of tension, whether
that's history, theology, or whether the
way things in scripture don't always
line up as as neat as we would like
them.
Uh I was talking to someone this week uh
because they were talking saying saying,
"Oh, li you you call to liberal theology
because I listen to Walton." We we have
um interview John Walton here.
He's not any better. [laughter]
Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah. When I think when I think of when
I think of liberal theologians, he
doesn't even
he doesn't make the but
the categories are very subjective. You
can you can you can go online and look
up find Michael Bird fundamentalist
theologian. So people in Australia think
I'm a raving fundamentalist right-wing
lunatic.
People in America think I am a radical
left-wing liberal, [clears throat]
you know. So
so in Australia they think of me as a
right-wing like you know Christian
nationalist. In America they think I'm a
communist leftwing. It's just so weird.
So, I would love to get the two groups,
you know, together like a kind of the I
hate Michael Bird society and bring them
all together and and see how they they
both dislike different things about me.
But maybe that means I'm in the right
place. I'm in the right place. I've got
I've got people who don't like what I do
from different angles.
And and the point that I wanted to make
is that I said you want precision. You
want historical precision uh theological
precision. Uh meaning that exactly what
uh you want to know exactly what
happened. And that type of precision
comes from um the enlightenment. It
comes from the liberal from the from the
liberal um mindset.
Yeah.
So [laughter]
yeah, I mean at one level seeking
precision is not too bad. wanting
wanting to be accurate, wanting to, you
know, um, rightly handle the word of God
is is not a bad thing, but you've got to
deal with the phenomena of the text. And
when you wrestle with the phenomena,
things may not always add up neatly the
way that you like. If you're expecting
the Bible to um balance like a
mathematical formula, you're going to be
disappointed. It's more like watching a
movie. And sometimes you struggle to
follow the plot or to find or to realize
what the main purpose of the movie or is
the movie fiction or is it based on a
real story? Sometimes you never really
know.
Like the Mandalorian I struggle a lot to
follow it. [laughter]
I prepare myself.
If you think that's not based on a true
story, Louis
Yes, I know. I know. But it was wants to
say something. [laughter]
Two things. The first thing is Vardman.
The second thing is about when
um I was uh talking with people these
days and they were surprised that Paul
use different the the meaning of
spirit field than than for example Luke
and they were like wow and
yeah that is true. I mean in Luke Acts
the spirit is associated with God's
promise, God's power.
Um it sort of animates it animates
Jesus. Jesus is filled with the Holy
Spirit. Similarly in the uh you the
apostles they're filled with the Holy
Spirit. Whereas in Paul there's a little
bit of that but it's also how the spirit
communicates the work of Christ to us.
That aspect is missing.
from the book of Acts.
Well, um she's ask she's she's talking
about that because she's doing a a a
very um thorough uh book study on Luke.
U is and um and she's using um um the
the study Bible. Brow wanted to um Berl
is doing a very thorough study on the
book of Luke
and um and she's using the the the Bible
the the the Bible background study Bible
from Walton and and Kener and she's
using some other books which which which
others uh because that's in Spanish.
It's a huge humongous Bible. It's a
humongous Bible. Yeah.
Yes. the charismatic theology of Rosher
Snat. Also the IBP Bible commentary from
Kener. Um
and I just gave her today
the grand commentary from Logos.
Yes. And I and I just u um gave her for
because I got it from from Cle. I I I
gave her the Hustto Gonzalez. Um
Oh yes.
Axe. Axe. So that's from our from our
perspective from our Latino. Actually,
actually I'm doing also some
support
some support uh with uh the New
Testament in its war because people need
some some theology there because it's
important
and Kia has said that it's going to send
her the copy. So, so next year we're
gonna have [laughter] to have you and
and hopefully and hopefully Tom as well
so we can talk about it.
Yeah.
All right. So, we move on. Um, so you
mentioned before uh regarding uh reading
the Bible christolog christoologgically
and this is one of the really things
when I came to really is really struck
me. This is uh going back to 1997 again.
So reading the Bible christoologgically
without forcing the text. We're not like
Lutheran or like Luther that he saw
Christ under every rock under every
page. So you have warned against Jesus
forcing Jesus into every detail of the
Old Testament in ways that ignore the
original meaning of the text. How can
Christians read the Bible uh the whole
Bible as a story that culminates in
Christ while still respecting the
original message of each passage?
Yeah. I mean let me let me explain what
I mean by this. So when you read the
story of David and Ba Sheba in the Old
Testament where David is behaving very
badly,
um the moral of the story is not like
well David sucks but don't worry we've
got a new David. Um that's the main I
mean that's the as if that's the main
point.
I think the main point is don't do the
horrible evil stuff David did. I mean
that's that's a big part of it. Don't do
what what David did was very bad. don't
be doing that. So that that's I think
that's one part of it. But as you read
the whole um Old Testament, you can read
it as an analogy
as a pro as propos as a prophecy as a
type or as a pattern. So Adam is an a
prototype of Christ. uh David is you
know establishing the Davidic covenant
in which you know Jesus would be the son
of David when proverbs 8 talks about the
wisdom of God um it's clearly can be
identified with Jesus similarly with the
various you know messianic parts of the
old testament you know Isaiah 9 Jeremiah
23 there's all sort so you can see
various types patterns prophecies and
preparations for Jesus So, I'm I'm not
denying that and you can find a number
of very good biblical theology works
that will bring that in. But
that that is an addition to not to the
exclusion of a historical reading, an
ethical reading or a a reading of the
Old Testament that also, you know,
speaks about even the church as the
people of God. So I I just want to add
more dimensions
rather than everybody rush to the um
what do we call it? Yeah.
what whatever word you call it
rather than do that as the first thing
make that the last thing you do think
how does this passage
prepare for anticipate provide a tight
pattern a prophecy or an analog
of Christ and it'll be different on
different parts of the scripture
depending where you're at on a given
time
I like what you said before that to
understand the scripture from where it
is coming from
um and I can think of when Paul says
there's no one righteous not even one
and people say see this is a
universality of of of men but then when
you read Genesis and you find out that
Noah was righteous Job was righteous and
other people were righteous then then
you have to that's where I think the our
previous questions they say well
Paul said this but this part of the
Bible says this is there a contradiction
and no you to understand uh the context
that Paul is using taking this from and
you D your commentary on Romans so you
you would know
yes
well uh just to go on um B you want to
do the next question uh
yes
so h you have spent many years serving
both in the academy and in the church in
your experience what does the church
often misunderstand about biblical
scholarship
And what do scholars often misunderstand
about the local church?
Yeah, sometimes uh the the church can
have the view of the academy
as if academics know all the facts and
all the truth that they that they've got
like the little laboratory
up in the university and they they've
got it all figured out. Uh they don't um
because in the academy we debate each
other all the time about you know
sources of Isaiah um you know dating of
the gospels. So the the they they don't
have anything everything worked out.
They're they're arguing amongst
themselves. Theories come and go all the
time. Uh I think the the other view that
you can get
is that and this is partly true that the
academy is very stale, dry,
cerebral, you know, which it undoubtedly
can be, but it's not exclusively that
way. uh or that the academy is filled
with people who just want to go around
mocking undermining people's faith. Um
you know the the academy is filled with
all sorts of people. People who are
Christians, diverse type of Christians,
non-Christians,
ex-Christians,
there's a diverse array of people, but
not all of them are waking up thinking,
how can I sabotage other people's faith?
So I mean those are the things I wish
the [clears throat] church knew about
the academy. Uh what I wish the academy
knew knew more about the church is that
most Christians at least you know in in
my experience are not like some of the
stereotypes
that they have. Like, you know, like
when I talk to some American Christian
friends and I tell my strainer friends,
they they seem to think that all my
American friends walk around with a
Trump t-shirt and holding an American
flag and
with an M16 and, you know, praise God
and pass the ammo. Um, which is a I
mean, there are some like that. There
are a few.
I don't think that because I remember
Gupta and he's not like that.
Yeah,
he's from the west. He's from the west.
West people are not like that.
Yeah. So, you know, and you can't have a
stereotype of what Christian people are
like. And, you know, people of faith are
always trying to wrestle with
uh the the big questions, you know, in
our age, social, ethical, cultural, and
simply doing the best they can in light
of the resources, the stories they have,
the the commitments that the communities
that they're a part of. So, I think that
would probably help the academy to have
a more um
uh a more accurate and qualified view of
who church people are rather than think
of them as some sort of stereotypical
view.
Yes. You want to build on that? I I was
want to ask about uh for example we have
a a little bit problem here in internet
uh with the apology and they think that
they are using the academia for defend
the their faith but
what could you say about that for
example?
So was about the the the
what was that?
Academia. Academia.
Academia.
So yeah, look at look I mean I mean I'm
an academic so I can't be against all
academics. I mean you know I am one. But
academic theories rise and fall all the
time and what's in vogue in in one age
10 years time will be treated as par or
disproved. So it's okay to engage,
interact and utilize
academic research, but you've always got
to have a little bit of an asterisk to
say, you know, what are the conditions
or there there is another way of looking
at things or some scholars believe in a
contrary view or some scholars would
modify this a bit. So I think everything
has got to be nuanced and qualified. You
can't just latch on to the latest and
greatest theories because usually those
theories will become um par or outdated
at some point.
Yes, I know because people here tend to
use uh for example entrite said that
that's a holy word.
Yeah.
Oh yes. [laughter]
He his name
Yeah. Well, even even Tom Wright would
say, um, 80 I'm convinced that 80% of
what I'm telling you is absolutely
right. I just don't know which the 80%
is.
So, even even Tom would say 80% of what
I'm telling you is correct. 20% is
probably wrong. I just don't know which
the 20% is.
Yes. Yes. Uh, there's one uh question.
Um, I'm going to make it because it's a
bit long, Bill. I don't want you to to
read too much.
Yes.
Yeah. transformation versus consumerism.
In a culture, this is a long one. Um,
just listen to me, Mike. In a culture of
quick answers, self-improvement, and
endless content, many Christians
approach the Bible looking for practical
tips or immediate solutions. Yet, in
your book, you emphasize that scriptures
primary purpose is to form us in the
knowledge of God, faith, love, and hope.
How does our relationship with the Bible
change when we stop reading it merely
merely for information or advice and
begin allowing it to shape our character
and disciplehip?
Yeah, it's a very good question. I mean,
you can read the Bible as a source for a
system of philosophy or thought. You can
read the Bible looking for ethical
advice or you can read the Bible looking
for daily tips like you know today's tip
you know um you know you know you know
every day you can see like an like a Tik
Tok or Instagram like a really cool way
to get stains out of jeans like
everything is just like a little you
know a life hack. Everything's a life
hack. M [clears throat]
um the Bible does has have some good
life hacks you know Proverbs is a book
of life hacks you know that how to help
you through life but not everything is
in scripture gives you an instant payoff
and there's a lot of it it's by the slow
process of reading it just constantly
over and over that it becomes embied and
it becomes absorbed in your life your
thinking your values use your fears,
your imag your imagination, the way you
the way you conceive of the world, you
know, that becomes very very important.
And so regular diet of Bible reading,
Bible study, listening to sermons, maybe
listening to podcasts, reading books
about the Bible,
this will hopefully um shape you in a
very profound way. I mean, a good
example is, you know, I can't remember
every single meal that my parents made
for me, but the meal always sustained me
for what I needed in the coming days,
hours, and weeks. It's a thing for
scripture. Not everything in scripture,
you know, I I didn't get like the sugar
kit, you know, from everything, okay?
Not like everything that was really
good. I feel full and nourished, but it
it was having that effect on me even
though I didn't feel the the immediate
payoff from it. You know, you as you
take in scripture, you digest it and it
kind of then becomes part of your DNA.
Uh I I guess that's how I would put it
better
because you you you made this question
so I thought you more to
or else I have a another question. What
do you think that is the the most uh
difficult challenge for the next
generation in reading the Bible?
That is hard. That is hard. Um
I [clears throat] I think there there is
going to be I mean AI is changing the
world in a big way. And I mean you can
do some fun things with AI. I mean you
can do some really cool things. you can
always do some bad things. Um, so yeah,
I I don't want to see people getting
their Bible via AI. I think, you know,
that would be bad. So I I think I think
we're going to wrestle with a lot of the
technologies we have and how it affects
like I mean I'm I'm bit of an AI
optimist. I think there's going to be
some great tools and things we'll be
able to do with AI um in the future. And
by study like Logos Bible software, you
can you know integrate AI in that.
There's some really cool things. So
there's some ch some challenges like
that. Um otherwise I think it's going to
depend on local context. I think the
challenges that people face in Kenya,
India,
you know, Chile are going to be
different to what people are facing in
in Barus. So it's it's hard it's hard to
say. I think in Australia,
one of the things we're facing is you
you've got a slightly more pluralistic
country in some sense. I think we are
becoming more more diverse.
Monoculture. Remember mono?
Monocultural. No. [laughter]
Yeah. No. Despite what Pauline Hansen
thinks.
Yes.
I don't think we're going to become
monocultural anytime soon.
Keep SBS. Keep SPS, please.
Yeah. [laughter] Yeah.
Yes.
Yeah. Yeah. I mean, this this is an
inside joke for his brains. Yeah. I
mean, I don't think that's going to
change. I don't think I would. I mean, I
I like I like my my I like my um
I like taco Tuesday and Indian food on
Thursday. So, I I don't really want to
be monocultural.
Um but I think we're going to, you know,
have to think more about how we do it in
the culture. I mean, I've been reading
about Scotland and the church there is
really depressing. The church in
Scotland
um in the over the space of about one
and a half generations has just
died. The church of Scotland is selling
[snorts] 40% of its property. Um so
places like Scotland need to be
re-evangelized.
Uh and it's not going to be the
Presbyterians. It will probably be the
Pentecostals who do it. I think soon the
main the only churches left in Scotland
will probably be the Pentecostal
churches or the charismatic churches
which I don't know what what John Knox
would have made of that the uh the guy
who helped bring the reformation to
Scotland
but I so I think there going to be
different challenges in different places
of the world certain parts of the world
like Scotland need to be re-evangelized
in places like say India I think the
church needs more protection for you
know religious freedom, their ability to
um
carry out their faith without
persecution or harassment or
discrimination from the government. um
you know in a in America I mean you've
got the challenge both of Christian
nationalism but also the temptation of
sort of you know some very progressive
left-wing views that touch every aspect
of culture and they kind of want a a
government who's more
uh you know somewhat I mean a little bit
more authoritarian to make sure their
progressive policies affect all aspects
of society. I mean that can that can be
an element too. So everywhere you go in
the world I think there's going to be
different there's going to be different
challenges people are facing but I take
heart from the fact that whether you
live in you know Delhi Brisbane Bornaris
uh you know Jesus Christ is still Lord.
Yes. Uh this is u I just want to show
you uh come here. I want to uh you know
this man. Yeah. [laughter]
Yeah.
So, no. Come here. Come closer. So, so,
so, um, so this is the man that says
that you are like Austin Powers.
Yes. [laughter]
Yeah. Well, he can hear you. He can hear
you.
Well, if I put my glasses on, it looks
more authentic.
Look, he's putting
the glasses.
The [laughter] glasses. Okay.
It was nice seeing you.
Yeah.
And he had Indian food today. Um,
quite spicy.
Uh, yeah. Quite spicy. No, this is a You
have to put it in.
You have to Yes. Yes. Um, one last
question and I think this is the most
important question. On the 20th of the
6, 226, Mike, you have to know the
answer for this.
Okay.
Australia, Argentina, who's going to win
the World Cup.
[laughter]
Oh, well, I would say my money if I had
to pick between them, I think
Argentina's got a better chance,
okay,
of winning it. Um, I wonder
I think France or Spain are probably the
favorites. France or Spain. Um,
I would like to see a a I thought I I
would like to see a new country win it
besides Germany, Brazil, Argentina,
France. I'd like to see someone else
like I don't know, Croatia, maybe even
New Zealand. I mean,
oh yes,
I think someone else deserves to win it
for once. So, you know, we we'll see
what happens. I was a little bit sad. A
Australia lost to the USA 2-0. That was
sad.
Yes, that's what you rugby. Yeah, that
that's what I was I was looking at you
and you were yawning. I said, "Oh, man."
He woke up in the morning, he saw the
game and and the you've been feeling bad
all day. [laughter]
What about you? What about you, Ver? Who
are you are you rooing for? [laughter]
Uh, well, I'm not really cheering for
any Oh, this ver
from Mexico.
Mexico. [laughter]
the um BO is um she she's a you know
she's totally Argentina [laughter]
and wearing blue you know
anyway. Go. Yep.
I was thinking that um for the next
generation here in Latin America with
the AI we we will
have a better education
and that's important because uh we are
like 50 years
from from here and
50 years. [laughter]
Yeah. Well, I mean, the thing I'm
worried about is people getting more of
their education on YouTube rather than
from anywhere else. Now, maybe there'll
be some very good YouTube shows like
like this one.
Amen.
That'll be fine. That'll be fine.
But there's also a lot of weird stuff on
YouTube you got to you got to watch out
for.
And it's it's amazing. Um let just to
let you know how far we are sometimes.
There are some seminaries that
contemporary theology. It's Paul Tilich
and and Bulman. That's contemporary.
Oh wow.
And I said this is a
it's like 1970s.
It's 1970s 1960s uh things and and uh
and and there are people my age teaching
that that that's contemporary theology.
So imagine what they've been taught. So
So and one of those
Luther Luther is
contemporary. Yes.
Luther Lutheran Calvin. Yeah.
Yes. There's an advertisement. There's
an advertisement that you want to know
contemporary theology, you're going to
learn Martin Luther. I said my my god,
what's going on in Latin America? But
anyway, Mike, thank you very much uh for
your time. Uh thank you for giving us
this uh interview. Uh there's another
book by you is translating
[clears throat] to Spanish uh about
Christology. Maybe we can arrange
something in the future because because
Christologology is a big thing in Latin
America. Colombia, they they have
unitarians in Colombia. It's like it's
like a hot bed of junarianism.
Unitarianism. They even call themselves
differently now because they're so much
me last words.
They have struggles with theos.
Theoto. Oh yes. Yes. In Latin America.
Yeah. If Latin America, if you believe
in Theotocos, you are a heretic.
If you believe in what?
Theotocos.
The mother of God.
Yes. Mother of God. If you believe that
and if you confess that, Christians
don't confess that. We we're not
Catholics because of that because of the
opposition to Catholicism.
Yeah.
I once had a student I I taught on the
Trinity and he said, "Oh, I didn't think
we believe that Catholic stuff." It's
like Catholics believe in the Trinity.
Catholics are bad people. Um therefore
we I mean Yeah. You Yeah, you can't do
that. That's just weird.
Yeah. I mean, Catholics also believe 2
plus two equals four.
That doesn't mean it equals five.
Yes. So in Latin America uh they see me
uh some people as suspect not as an a
Christian but suspect because I because
I defend theotocos and and therefore I'm
with the Catholics
and I said no but that's a Christian
position. So any so just to let you know
just to let you know the the things the
thing we're fighting against uh it's um
also they are preto
the preto yes preto as well a lot of
predtoist and um
full pretoist
full predtoist wow that's that's a lot
of predtoism [laughter]
yes full on so anyway thank you thank
you Mike so we're gonna have uh have you
hopefully sometime soon if you don't
mind you give me one minute after we
finish and so I can tell you something,
we can go over something and and and
that's it. Um um check the notes under
say in Spanish.
Mike, you um you have um you give us
your plugs. You you have a Substack.
Yes, Substack. Uh uh michael
fbird.substack.com.
You
can find me on Twitter at mbird12
and through um ask entrite anything
or my own YouTube channel early
Christian history.
Yes. Okay. So there you go. We're going
to put those those uh links in in in the
notes. Thank you very much. Um, we'll
see you next and may the best team win
the World Cup. Amen. [laughter]
Okay, goodbye.